Simone BALLOCCU



PROFILE

Computer scientist with 6+ years of experience in NLP & AI research, and author of 17 peer-reviewed NLP publications. I was involved in several EU-funded projects, including Horizon 2020, ERC and EU Erasmus Traineeship. I implemented and evaluated several AI resources for behaviour change, including conversational agents and datasets for nutrition counselling and motivational interviewing.

CONTACT DETAILS

- @ balloccu@ufal.mff.cuni.cz
- **\(+39 345 595 1827**
- uccollab.github.io
- Room 230, IMPAKT Building,
 V Holešovičkách 2, 180 00 Praha 8,

Prague, CZ

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Citizenship: Italian

Languages: Italian (Native),

English (IELTS-C1)

SKILLS

- Python, Java, C, R, Scala, Javascript
- Machine learning model training, analysis, bias and fairness assessment.
- Implementation and evaluation of NLP systems in the context of behaviour change, counselling and mental health.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

POSTDOC 2023.07-pres.

♀ Charles University (CZ)

> ERC-2021-STG, NG-NLG project

⋄ Topics: Neuro-symbolic NLG approaches; Large Language Models controllability.

VISITING RESEARCHER

2022.05-2022.10

♥ Philips Research (NL)

> Horizon 2020, Philhumans project

⋄ Topics: Use of Large Language Models in Counselling; Al-driven activity tracking for behaviour change.

VISITING RESEARCHER

2020.07-2021.05

♥ Philips Research (NL)

> Horizon 2020, Philhumans project

⋄ **Topics:** AI-oriented counselling datasets.

ASSISTANT RESEARCHER

2018.12-2019.09

♀ University of Cagliari (IT).

> Sardegna Ricerche, DoUtDes project

⋄ Topics: Al-driven marketing campaigns for companies

ASSISTANT RESEARCHER

2017.01-2019.09

Q University of Cagliari (IT).

> Sardegna Ricerche, OKGraph project

⋄ Topics: Unsupervised NLP algorithm for knowledge extraction from free text.

EDUCATION

РнD in Artificial Intelligence

2019.10-2023.05

Q University of Aberdeen (UK).

> Marie Skłodowska-Curie ESR - PHilhumans project (ESR-7)

> Thesis title: Emotion-aware and tailored diet coaching with Natural Language Generation.

M.Sc in Computer Science

2017.10-2019.09

Q University of Cagliari (IT).

> Thesis title: Unsupervised Hypernym Discovery from plain text.

B.Sc in Computer Science

2013.10-2017.09

Q University of Cagliari (IT).

> Thesis title: Unsupervised learning of IS-A relations from plain text.

TEACHING

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Winter 2023 - Spring 2024

 \mathbf{Q} Charles University (CZ).

> NPFL099: Statistical Dialogue Systems

> Responsibilities: Marking and running lectures.

DEMONSTRATOR

Spring 2021 & Spring 2022

♀ University of Aberdeen (UK).

> CS551H: Natural Language Generation

> **Responsibilities:** Demonstrating and running lab practicals.

- Extrinsic and Intrinsic NLP system evaluation; Human-in-the-loop and Expert-in-the-loop evaluation.
- LLMs prompt engineering including zero and few-shot prompting, prompt injection and red-teaming.

INVITED LECTURER

Spring 2020 & Spring 2021

Q University of Cagliari (IT).

- > SC/0132/EN: Natural Language Processing
- > Responsibilities: Running invited lectures and related labs.

MENTORING

Experience co-supervising students at both Bachelor's and Master's level

♀ Charles University (CZ)

present

- > 1 Bachelor's student (in progress)
- > 1 Master's student (in progress)
- **♀** University of Aberdeen (UK)

2023-2024

- > 1 Master's student
- ♥ University of Utrecht (NL)> 1 Master's student

2021-2022

♀ University of Cagliari (IT)

2020-2021

> 2 Bachelor's students

ORGANISATIONAL EXPERIENCE

CO-CHAIR 2024

- The 2nd Workshop on Practical LLM-assisted Data-to-Text Generation (Practical D2T 2024 @ INLG 2024)
- The International Workshop on Human-Centered Modeling and Adaptation for Digital Transformation (HUMAD 2024 @ ACM UMAP 2024)
- The 4rd Workshop on Human Evaluation of NLP Systems (HumEval 2024 @ LREC-COLING 2024)

ORGANIZING COMMITTEE MEMBER

2023

- The 3rd Workshop on Human Evaluation of NLP Systems (HumEval 2023 @ RANLP 2023)
- The 16th International Natural Language Generation Conference (INLG 2023)
- The 24th Annual Meeting of the Special Interest Group on Discourse and Dialogue (SIGDial 2023)

PROPOSALS

META LLAMA IMPACT GRANT (AWAITING FEEDBACK)

Title: LLama 2 for efficient communication with autistic

students

Members: Charles University (CZ), Institute of Neuropsychiatric

Care (CZ), University of Aberdeen (UK), LuxAI (LU).

Amount: \$500,000.

Role: Coordinated proposal writing.

EPSRC (AWAITING FEEDBACK)

2023

2024

Title: Using Large Language Models in Dietary Chatbots

Members: University of Aberdeen (UK), Charles University (CZ), University of

Manchester (UK), University of Stirling (UK).

Amount: £1,193,716.

Role: Contributed to proposal writing.

RESEARCH AND PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed publications: 17

Google h-index: 7 Google i-10 index: 4 Citations: 149

Link to the complete list of publications: Google Scholar

> Selected peer-reviewed publications

 "Leak, Cheat, Repeat: Data Contamination and Evaluation Malpractices in Closed-Source LLMs"

Simone Balloccu, Patrícia Schmidtová, Mateusz Lango, Ondřej Dušek. In Proceedings of the 18th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), Mar 2024

CORE Rank: A

P Best Non Publicized Paper Award

 Are Experts Needed? On Human Evaluation of Counselling Reflection Generation.

Zixiu Wu, <u>Simone Balloccu</u>, Ehud Reiter, Rim Helaoui, Diego Reforgiato Recupero, Daniele Riboni.

In Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), Jul 2023. CORE Rank: A*

Anno-MI: A Dataset of Expert-Annotated Counselling Dialogues.

Zixiu Wu, <u>Simone Balloccu</u>, Vivek Kumar, Rim Helaoui, Ehud Reiter, Diego Reforgiato Recupero, Daniele Riboni.

In ICASSP 2022 - 2022 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), May 2022.

CORE Rank: B